"Do Healthy Fast Food Options
Lead to Healthier Choices?"
In 2017, and to much fanfare,
menu labeling for calorie counts
began to be mandated
in national chain restaurants.
I mean shouldn't consumers
have the knowledge needed
to make healthy eating
choices outside the home?
It just makes sense that caloric
information on menus will help
consumers limit food intake
to stay within daily energy needs,
but it didn't work. It turns out
calorie labels are not effective,
perhaps shaving on average an
insignificant 8 calories off of a meal.
You could have totally
predicted that. Why?
Just as one might divine the value
of front-of-pack traffic light labeling
from the ferocity of the food
industry response against it,
one could probably gauge
the futility of calorie labeling
by the ease at which some
regulations have been passed.
McDonald's voluntarily started
publishing calorie info
nationally back in 2012
after a labeling mandate
in New York City was found
to have no overall effect
on consumer behavior.
So studies suggest such labeling
could boost "perceptions of
the restaurant's concern
for consumers' well-being"
while carefully not undermining
any Big Mac attacks.
At the same time,
McDonald's announced plans
for adding seasonal
produce to their menu.
How cynical do you have to be not to
at least recognize that as a good thing?
Ironically, adding a healthy option
can actually drive people
to make even worse choices.
Ready to have your mind blown?
If you offer people a choice of side
dishes—something unhealthy
like French fries or something more
neutral like a baked potato—
only about 10% of individuals with high
self-control will splurge for the fries.
Good for them.
French fries are so unhealthy though
that as a public health do-gooder
you add a third option, an even
healthier option than the baked potato—
a side salad to appeal
to their better natures.
So then, instead of choosing
between an indulgent choice
and the more neutral baked potato,
they have their pick of
the indulgent choice, the neutral
choice, or an even healthier choice.
Even if everyone doesn't choose
the salad, more will go for
the middle-ground baked potato
over the fries, right?
So how much farther does
French fry fancying fall
by adding the salad option to the
mix? It shoots up, tripling to 33%.
Without the salad option,
only 1 in 10 chose the fries,
but that jumped to a third of people
just at the sight of salad.
The same thing happens when
you offer people the choice between
a bacon cheeseburger, a chicken
sandwich, or a veggie burger.
In a "No Healthy Option"
scenario where people were
offered the cheeseburger, a chicken
sandwich, or a fish sandwich,
17% chose the burger.
Swap out the fish sandwich
for a veggie burger
and bacon cheeseburger
preference doubled to 37%.
How can just seeing a healthy option push
people to make unhealthier choices?
The paper described in these series
of experiments was entitled
"Vicarious Goal Fulfillment: When the
Mere Presence of a Healthy Option
Leads to an Ironically
Indulgent Decision."
The thought is that seeing
the salad or veggie burger,
people make the mental note to choose
that at some nebulous next time,
thereby giving them the
excuse to indulge now.
See, there's a fascinating glitch of
human psychology called self-licensing.
This is when we unwittingly justify
doing something that draws us away
from our goals after we've just done
something that brings us towards them,
like justifying eating a donut because
you lost so much weight last week.
We reward ourselves with an
indulgence that sets us back.
If you give smokers
" vitamin C supplements,"
they subsequently
smoke more cigarettes
than if you give smokers what
you explain are "placebo" pills,
even though both groups were
given identical sugar pills.
The group who thought they were
taking supplements smoked
nearly twice as much, perhaps
thinking at some subconscious level
that since they had just done
something good for their health,
they could afford to "live a little,"
which may have in effect indeed
occasioned them to live a little less.
You can see how this could
translate into our lifestyle arenas.
Those given placebo pills they
believed to be dietary supplements
not only expressed less desire to
subsequently engage in exercise,
but followed through by
walking about a third less.
Compared to those who were
told the pills were placebos,
misled participants were also
more likely to choose a buffet
over what was described
as a "healthy, organic meal."
Would they eat more too?
A seminal study entitled
"The liberating effect of weight loss
supplements on dietary control"
put it to the test.
Participants were randomized
to take a known placebo
or a purported weight loss supplement—
actually just the same placebo—
and later covertly observed at a buffet.
Not only did the supplement
subjects eat more food,
they chose less healthy items.
They also ate about 30% more candy
in a bogus "taste test" and
ordered more sugary drinks.
Hence, the investigators
concluded, "people who rely
on dietary supplements
for health protection
may pay a hidden price: the curse
of licensed self-indulgence."
So, circling back, what the vicarious
goal fulfillment studies added is that
not only does making progress towards
a goal rationalize decision making
that undermines us, but even just
considering making progress
can have a similar licensing effect.
Note the study subjects were
not only moved to make
the unhealthier choice,
but the unhealthiest choice.
You'd think that even if people didn't
go for the salad or veggie option,
the presence of a healthier alternative
might at least have encouraged them
to choose something in-between: not
as healthy, but not the unhealthiest,
but instead it moved people
in the opposite direction.
Compared to the "No Healthy Option"
of chocolate-covered Oreos,
regular Oreos, or golden Oreos,
adding a "lower-calorie" Oreo option
doubled the likelihood that the study
participants would go straight
for the most indulgent
chocolate-covered option.
This is attributed to another illogical
quirk of human psychology
indelicately named the
"what the hell effect."
This is when one forbidden cookie
can lead dieters to eat the whole bag.
Once you've already strayed
from your goals,
well then, why not go all the way?
So once people decide they're
going to get that salad next time
and spoil themselves just this once,
they might as well go for
the most indulgent choice.
The halo of healthy foods
can even warp our perceptions.
Show weight-conscious people
a burger and nothing else,
then ask them to estimate the number
of calories, and the average answer
is 734 calories.
Now show folks
the exact same burger
accompanied by 3 celery sticks,
and they guess the total
comes out to 619 calories.
Did they think the celery
had negative calories?
No, most knew the
celery had calories, too,
but just the juxtaposition
of the burger with the celery
made the burger seem healthier.
The same thing happens
when you add an apple
to a bacon-and-cheese
waffle sandwich,
a side salad to beef chili, or some
carrots next to a cheese steak.
About a hundred calories
appear to disappear.
Health halo effects may explain
why people are more likely
to order a dessert and
more sugary drinks
with a "healthier" sub at Subway
versus a Big Mac at McDonald's,
even though the sub used in the study—
filled with ham, salami, and pepperoni—
had 50% more calories to begin with.
Even just a reference
to healthy foods can do it.
Show people a picture of a Big Mac and
people estimate it has 646 calories.
Okay, then just add the words
"For your health, eat at least five
fruits and vegetables per day,"
and all the sudden, the same burger
in the same ad was thought
to only have 503 calories.
Merely offering or even
promoting salads and fruit
can bring McDonald's accolades
and bolster consumer loyalty
without, ironically,
helping their health.